in this system design interview scenario
we'll break down the design of a Twitter
like up covering everything from the
initial requirements to the high level
architecture so let's start with the
background of X or Twitter we know that
people can follow others and this can be
mutual meaning others can follow them
back so people can follow each other but
naturally some users will end up being
more popular meaning with more followers
and this indicates that it will be a
read heavy system as most users only
browse the tweets while a small
percentage will be actively creating
these tweets and the typical tweet looks
something like this people can tweet
text up to 280 characters and optionally
they can also include images and videos
and we also have some interactions at
the bottom like users can comment
retweet or like other people's tweets
and now let's prioritize these features
and see which are the must have features
for us the core features that we will
focus on are the followings users need
to be able to follow other people we
will support the tweeting functionality
users need to be able to create tweets
and and this tweet length can be up to
280 characters for most users and we
will also support images and videos but
we won't be covering the premium feature
of extended tweet length in this basic
design so the maximum tweet length is
still 280 characters we will also
support the news feed users need to see
tweets from other users they follow and
on X for example we have the for you and
following feeds the for you feed is a
bit algorithmic while the following is
just showing the tweets of people that
you follow and we will only cover the
this type of Feed in our system design
with that let's move on to
non-functional requirements and let's
consider the scale and performance
demands of this system let's start with
the scale research shows that X
currently has 500 million monthly active
users and let's assume that out of these
200 million are daily active users and
the typical user here on average follows
around 4 100 people with this
information we can calculate the read
and write volumes let's start with the
read volume with our assumption which is
typically daily active users read on
average 100 tweets per day that will be
around 200 Millions time 100 and we will
have 20 billion reads daily and when it
comes to the right volume we can assume
that daily active user typically creates
10 tweets per day significantly lower
than the read volume and that will be
200 Millions time 10 and that will be 2
billion new tweets daily in our system
and regarding the data size that will be
storing each of these tweets can be 1
kiloby on average if it's text only but
if it contains attachments like images
and videos then it can range from 1
megab to 5 mgab but to simplify let's
assume that an average tweet size will
be 1 megabytes even though some tweets
with media could be larger and this
means that we are dealing with 200
million time 1 Megabyte and we will be
storing 20 petabytes of data each day
and some key takeaways that we can do
from here is that this is clearly a read
heavy system meaning we should optimize
for efficient reads and the data storage
requirements are very large so we need
to consider scalable storage options and
also handling the load of popular users
with millions of followers will present
a unique Challenge on its own and with
this we can move on to the API design of
our system we'll assume that all
requests are authenticated with some
sort of off service before reaching to
our API and we also have the user ID in
each request and we won't dive deep into
this off service as in system design
interviews usually you don't focus on
such services and the interviewer
usually assumes that you know how to
authenticate us users so we can start
sketching our core endpoints and the
first one will be for creating tweets
this will be a post request to/ tweets
and in the request we will have the
content which is the string text of the
tweet it will contain media IDs which is
an array of media IDs for images and
videos and from the server s we will
obtain this user ID which is received
from the authentication Service and
we'll also receive the created ad or
some sort of Tim stamp which is set by
the server at the time of the creation
and in case of the successful response
we will include the ID of this created
tweet we will also attach the Tim stamp
when the Tweet was created and also a
success bullion which indicates whether
the Tweet was created or not the next
endpoint will be for our feed which is
the get to/ feed in the request we can
optionally include the cursor of string
which is a pagination token to fetch the
next set of tweets and also from the
server side we will receive this user ID
so that we know which feed we need to
return and in the response we will
receive an array of tweet of objects and
each of them will contain media IDs
which is an array of strings of images
and videos and for each of them we will
also contain the created at timestamp
and also the next corser which is a
pagination token to fetch the next set
of tweets the next Endo that we will
have is for users to be able to follow
each other and that will be a post
request to slf SL the ID of the user
that we want to follow and this can be
pretty simple we can just return the
success bullion which indicates whether
the follow operation was successful or
or not or we can just return a success
status code and that's it and similar to
this we will have the unfollow endpoint
which is actually not a separate
endpoint but we will just change the
method of this to be delete to slf
follow SL the user ID that we want to
unfollow and now let's move on to the
high level design of this system a quick
note if you're enjoying this so far I
have a free system design course in our
school Community where you can learn
more about each of the components that
we'll be discussing here let's visualize
the major components of this system we
will have the mobile app and also the
client and this is where users will
interact with our system creating tweets
viewing feeds and following or
unfollowing others in front of all the
requests we will have a load balancer
which will distribute the requests
across multiple observers and for now we
can use the layer for load balancing
which operates based on the TCP port
numbers and IP addresses and this is
suitable for now for Distributing
General traffic without needing to
inspect the content of the requests but
we'll change the this layer soon in the
scaling section and you'll see exactly
why we need to change it next in front
of this load balancer we will have the
API servers and this will handle the
requests that we created earlier like
fetching tweets filtering feeds or
interacting with the database and cache
and rendering responses back to the
client and we also need to decide on the
database whether we are going to use no
SQL or SQL type of database while no SQL
databases will be great here at handling
large amounts of unstructured data but
actually a relation database is better
suited for our use case due to the need
for complex relationships and Joints
between the users and tweets so we'll
use a relational database something like
MySQL or poster SQL to store the
structured data regarding our database
schema we will have a followers table
and here we will store the FY ID which
is a string the ID of the user that is
being followed and also the follower ID
which is the ID of the user that follows
this followe and we can Index this table
on follower ID to efficiently retrieve
all the people user follows and these
are also foreign Keys which are pointing
to the users table in the users table we
will have the basic information like ID
of a user username email and also create
that which is the creation date of the
account and from here we will have the
ID as primary key which links to the
tweets table in the tweets table we will
have the Tweet ID which is a unique
identifier for each tweet we will have
the content which is the text content of
this tweet and also created at which is
the Tim stamp that the Tweet was created
and here optionally we will also have
the media IDs which is the IDS of the
images videos and other media files and
other than that we may have some small
tables like likes which just joins the
tweets and users tables based on the
Tweet ID and user ID and in front of our
database we will have a cache layer
something like redis or mcache to store
frequently accessed data like popular
tweets or popular user profiles and this
will reduce the load on our database and
it will also improve our read latency
and in our case we can use lru cache
which is least recently used and this
will help us keep the most relevant data
in the cache and remove the others that
are not relevant anymore and regarding
the images videos or other media files
we need some sort of object storage
something like awss fre or Google Cloud
Storage this is used to store large
media files like the images and videos
that we are going to store and we will
have the associated Tweets in our
database and the link to the media files
which is inside of this object storage
so with this setup the apis will get the
tweets from the database and the clients
will query the object storage for the
images and videos but we can take this a
step further and introduce a pool based
CDN which will cach our media files
closer to the users geographically and
this will further reduce the latency and
it will also improve the user experience
and we'll use a full based CDN which
fetches the content from the origin
object storage on the first request and
also caches it for the next incoming
requests now with our current system
design the database is the primary
bottleneck and if you have something
that will fail that will be the database
first so we need to scale our database
first let's see how we can scale the
reads to scale the reads we can
introduce read replicas of our primary
database and these replicas are just
copies of the primary database but they
are only used for read operations so
we'll have one master replica or leader
which is responsible for writing to the
database and we'll have many read
replicas or followers which are
responsible for retrieving data to our
apis and in addition to these replicas
we also have the caching layer that we
are leveraging and popular tweets and
user profiles will be stored there and
this will also reduce the need to query
the database for frequently accessed
data now let's talk about scaling the
rights as one right database might not
be enough for this system and to scale
our right we can sh the database or one
specific table like tweet table which
will be used the most based on the user
ID and this means that will horizontally
partition the table or database across
multiple database servers and each of
these sharts will be responsible for
storing the tweets for a specific range
of user IDs and to determine the
location of the data will use a
technique called consistent hushing to
map the user ID to shards which will
ensure the distribution of data and it
will also minimize the impact of adding
or removing shards so we'll add the
shards to the database system system and
to further optimize performance we can
separate read and write operations
meaning we can have read apis and also
write apis and this will be separate
apis each will be responsible for its
own thing so the right API will only be
responsible for writing to the leader
database and the read apis will be
responsible for reading from the cache
or from the follower databases and to
achieve this we need to change the layer
of the load balancer we need to change
that to layer seven which is the
application layer and this ler allows us
to make routing decisions based on the
content of the request itself such as
HTTP methods where we can direct the get
requests to the read apis and the post
delete requests to the write apis or we
can also use the URL path to be more
specific and this is perfect for our
scenario and finally let's also talk
about handling the peak load of our
current system to manage the peak craing
we can introduce a message cue something
like Kafka so when a user creates a
tweet the API server will publish a
message to this message queue and we can
have a temporary cache and we can store
the copy of this tweet to the temporary
cache while it's being written to the
database and during that time the users
can read this tweet from the temporary
cache and once the Tweet will be written
in our database it will also be added to
our lru cache and we can remove it from
the temporary cache and this will be the
final look of our high level
architecture obviously Real World
Systems like Twitter are more complex
than this with many challenges like
concurrent updates and also the for you
algorithmical feed with pagination twet
ordering and many other challenges but
in real system design interview you
typically won't focus on that for you
feet or that complex tasks and this
should be enough for you to have the
high level overview and then you can
dive into specific areas in depth and
explore them on your own